so it's it's good to see the two of you
again and thanks again guy for inviting
me to that that drop-in video drop-in
session on Sunday that was quite
wonderful enjoyed it a lot yeah drop in
I brought one I just appreciate it you
making good time and drop in so you seem
particularly dropped in exactly how to
put it else to put it but just a sense
of like you just will Punk I appreciated
it there's a lot of good questions from
that group a lot of good questions yeah
it's a good group yeah well I appreciate
them watching the series so I thought
maybe we could follow up on the
discussion that johannes and i had on
Heidegger and the questions around
science technology and spirituality I I
think that would be a good place to
begin I'll pick up but and but guide we
could also weave it together with
perhaps you know the deal logos project
broadly construed that I think those two
should be brought into a deeper
conversation with each other and so I
think that would be a good place to pick
up pick up and sort of weave together
what do you guys think about that as a
proposal for going forward that sounds
great I could I could share to you some
of my thoughts about like kind of
tensions or questions that are I've been
walking around with this a couple things
like one is I just I I would like to get
on Piper's Heidegger's notion write
about about the technological age and
the history of being and they spent
precisely the history of metaphysics in
conversation with them with them in
nihilism and in combat in believing
crisis yes very much I think in seeing
because in my mind done one level I
think about it I'm like I don't know if
I actually have a different if there's a
difference there but I'm imagining
there's some key differences right but I
just
love to get them talking to each other
and just I would imagine they would
deeply inform one another in ways that
were would be really that's really good
and I think you're honest I we didn't
finish I don't think we actually caught
around to the topic of Heidegger's
thesis that the history of metaphysics
is the history of nihilism I think we're
we were just sort of broaching on it am
I am I remembering that correctly I
think that's about where we were and
we're just about to get onto that and of
course the connection to the meeting
crisis I think is is is pertinent and
relevant I start off the whole section
on the the prophets of the meaning
crisis with Heidegger because I think
he's pivotal figure so yeah I I would
like to to talk about that and that goes
towards sort of the broader topic that
I'm trying to explore you know and this
and the new series I have Boyce's with
Rob a key because I'm trying to get at
you know this relationship between
science spirituality and the meaning
crisis so that's that's one is getting
those talking to each other the other
one is just kind of a tension I notice
I'm having in let's just come about and
it's um
it I was really I want one of these
Johannes I really enjoyed your
conversation with your last conversation
with your teacher about about nihilism
yeah you would not oh yeah yeah excuse
me what was the name what was the name
evil ditching out oh yeah yeah yeah I
just I just really enjoy him a lot like
like his rigor of thought but let his
few at the same time just a real unique
being well but one of the things he
talked about was the how do we you know
you got that how do we respond to the
with all of being right and and what is
how do you respond to that and and I
think one of the things I'm I notice I
have a like a a wandering or attention
when I listen to other people and when I
myself is on one level I see a lot of
people so-called responding to it mm-hmm
right however it seems to me that in
some way the way that they're thinking
about it demonstrates the very embodies
the the in their response like furthers
the issue of Technology right kind of
like this notion of like turning the
world into a problem to solve
okay and just I just noticed like I I
think I have this sense of what
Heidegger's talking about with the with
temporality and like the understanding
of being is that it's it's actually we
are inside of it right
right there's a there's a quality of
like that it's not under our direct
control and like that there's something
in there about and given that right what
is the authentic response being immortal
right in being in touch with the actual
phenomena so that's like one of the
things that I'm noticing is in and just
also thinking about it in terms of like
the ecology of practices right right
right
and and I and you're John you're you're
you're my understanding of your repeated
insistence that not to imply an on to a
theology right yes like it's about the
process of exercising the machinery
directly and like we don't need to
assert we don't need to cert a being
right or God or something but there's a
mystery and in touchless that you can
get in it through the exercise of it
right and I I think there's like deep
parallels there but I dig irritated if
people a lot when they talk about like
this kind of mania of like it's up to us
to fix the world or something like that
you know and I there's a tension in
there for me so I mean they don't make
allow me to a couple issues I want to
frame and then maybe we'll let on us any
issues he wants to frame so in
connection
with your second point I'm interested in
putting into a more Claire clear and
clarifying discussion relationship what
the ontological aspects the existential
and the psychological aspects of the
meeting crisis are and because in
connection with that Kris and I have
been working on an article for the side
view on the symptomology of the meaning
crisis and trying to develop that and
then you know you probably know I think
you've seen this before you distinguish
between sort of reactive responses and
reflective responses and I think for the
project that we're trying to do I think
that's adequate but that pretty much
sits sort of the intersection that it
needs to be teased though better between
the cognitive and the existential but it
doesn't get too much into the
ontological and I'd like to get that a
little bit clearer and that might be a
way of going back to the first point of
clarifying the relationship between the
meaning crisis and nihilism and then the
other point that came up was which was a
point that you Honus and I were did talk
about quite a bit which is you know I'm
struggling for a verb here but it's not
quite adequate but something like the
Rican Sep xual ization but in a very
profound way of sacredness and what does
that mean for us now and what
relationship does that have it to my
first question is sacredness a category
for example that cuts across the
cognitive the existential and the
ontological is that precisely what it's
supposed to do for us and therefore
trying to situate it within any one of
those categories is a mistake but if it
is trans categorical like that then
what's our appropriate way of of
understanding and relating to it so
those are the two issues I'd like to
sort of try and get get clear about I'm
just one other thing in there that's
just the paper that you and Chris wrote
yeah it's so good
[Laughter]
we're gonna actually start off our our
our series of videos where we go through
the Platonic dialogues winning paper
because I think it it frames it
perfectly and grounds it and you know in
our time and related you there's a way
that you formulated the problem which I
just thought was I've just been thinking
about it ever since which is the loss of
the second person like post modernity is
the loss of the other basically in a
particular kind of way yes yeah that's
right and I had never thought about it
quite like that but there's something
about just that sense of where we're
blind right to what one presupposes what
gives a dye up a genuine dialogue owes
right yeah yeah yeah I think that that
goes towards both my questions I'm no
surprise because you know I'm posing the
question that I wrote the paper with
Chris so but the the idea that that the
logos might actually again cut across
the three categories and it might be a
place in which we're also finding a way
of re-enacting and therefore reimagining
in urban sense of the word imagine the
imaginal reimagining the sacred and so
I'm I would like to talk about that in
connection to the two questions I raised
yeah let me just briefly maybe summarize
with de Gennaro and I talked about some
something else
it was on Nietzsche and Heidegger on
definitions of nihilism and for
Nietzsche nihilism is that beings are
nothing beings are senseless they amount
to nothing while and and that for
Heidegger means that Nietzsche here
turns all of metaphysics on its head but
it's a physician why because he begins
with beings and then leaps to the
beingness of beings and then Hyde again
the second Nietzsche book rights or
argues that authentic nihilism
I'm listening mismos would mean not
meaninglessness in this sense that we
usually how we usually think of it but
what mean that being itself always
already stays away being itself amounts
to nothing and that's not a value
judgment that's not a moral problem but
being it is always already withdrawing
and then what metaphysics has perhaps
you could say failed to see or fail to
understand is that being itself is that
which withdraws self conceals self
denies itself and has instead posited
the beingness of beings right has
ratified being for example as a to come
back to what you mentioned John the
untrue theology comes posits being as
the causal soui that means the ground
that causes itself and tries to give
ultimate grounds and here we have as
Heidegger also says in connection to
Sciences which try to give the perfect
you know a ground for all beings whereas
what we perhaps in exercise can learn we
should learn is that ground always
withdraws that it's temporal is
historical yeah so those are just a
couple of thoughts maybe it's a
beginning so one quick one connection
and well maybe we can pick up we don't
have to do it immediately on that I'm
interested in nishitani stake on that as
in religion and nothingness in certain
enters into a long sort of reflection on
that and he he makes the argument that
Asian particularly Buddhist philosophy
has an advantage because it doesn't have
an established history of prioritising
being over non being and prioritizing
actuality over a possibility and that in
fact Taoism and Buddhism you see the
aucd inverse actually in a he and he
argues that it's that kind of ability to
stand on the inversion point between the
two
physics he talked about you know the the
pivot point and that's where you're
trying to get in your thinking right and
so you can pivot between these two and
you can get to this place where you do
this sort of fundamental aspect shift on
so you're not changing if this is the
right word I don't even know this right
word I seriously don't even know if it's
the right word but you're not changing
the fact of nihilism you're doing this
sort of fundamental aspect shift on it
yeah I mean from seeing it as some kind
of deep privation to seeing it as some
kind of deep affordance so I'd like I
think I think that's I'd like to pick up
on that too because I didn't ever get a
chance to talk about the Kyoto School in
this and and it's really interesting
because I think they're they're doing
some well I particularly think mr.
Tony's work is brilliant yeah so hide
again being in time says possibility
stands higher than actuality it's
vaguely sky this is the total it's an
inversion of the history of metaphysics
Hey perfectly clear actuality is higher
than possibility and actually subsumes
consumes all the possibility and that's
simply a dialectical version of
Aristotelian is intelligent and then
hide again word stays in hiding it you
know the cure to school of course
originates because they did they go to
fiber can listen to Heidegger yeah wow
this is all of a sudden someone we can
actually also understand you know this
hi to get in touch with Japanese
scholars throughout his life and there's
text dialog where up wish that he
synthesized from converse conversations
he had over his lifetime with scholars
from Japan where he says we do live in
different houses because we live in
different languages but there can there
is still a neighborhood it wouldn't make
sense to speak of a house without the
house is only a house of it's a
neighborhood with its surroundings its
landscape but another house another
village somewhere else and there must be
no I think this is what Heidi girls it
gives up even on the word of philosophy
right he says philosophy is over it's
again it's it comes to an end now the
thinking must break free and I think
this is this kind of because European
philosophy never had 2d
what we call metaphysics didn't have to
deal with Japanese thought it didn't
have to deal with Indian thought much it
was circling around itself and blahblah
absolute spirit
let me be your prophet but now it has to
deal with it and hiding it breaks free
from this and that that's I think where
we I think where we have to go is to
have this dialogue between these
different houses of meaning if you like
these different planes of existence
because exactly as you say it so they
don't think consider will be called
nihilism from a moral perspective I mean
we do bicho though this is dangerous
that don't go there don't go to what's
nothing but for someone like hide again
and for the Cure to school you begin
with there is nothing you have to accept
this withdrawal this denial concealment
ivy referred to it and only then all of
us weirdly enough beings light up again
in their wealth because they're no
longer attacked as standing reserve for
example that's a way of thinking of
beings as in terms of a beingness of
beings is something waiting to be
connected it's to connect it to thinking
of beings only insofar as they act and
picking up on this on the key of
actuality is you know how things act
right and which is different right right
right from from how they are and in the
sense of both you know the phenomena are
they shine into infinity as you said
they're also withdrawing at the same
time yeah this is what I think even
Aristotle shied away from this because
Dunamis which is the word Dunamis is
potentiality in Greek we get the word
dynamics for that in English Dunamis
carries with itself nothingness because
it's not yet actualized and what is not
yet actualized is of course there's the
nothing or you know some version of it
lingering there but that's something the
the west or Western thoughts or Western
philosophy metaphysics etcetera has been
scared off right away from both of you
know I'm a deep fan of Neoplatonism but
this
one area in which I have any criticism
of neoplatonism and the nishitani makes
it of course nothingness because you see
for example in platanus that
potentiality becomes equated with evil
explicitly now that that adds sort of a
that have an important call cultural
even ontological function because it
gave up I gave a locus for evil and
therefore rendered it in some sense
metaphysically intelligible right even
saying that it's a place of non
intelligibility only makes sense if you
can situate it within a field of
intelligibility right and so I get why I
get why that was an attractive idea
right I see why that's a very attractive
idea why people work adhere to it but I
think I think what I'm saying is I think
it's converging with your point is it
permanently besmirched you know
potentiality with you know the taint of
the chaotic and the evil and the demonic
and that's why it's very hard like what
I'm even trying to teach dynamical
systems and which is directly related to
Dynamis again both when I try to say
look you have to shift and I you know
I'll put a piece of chalk on a table and
I'll push it and I'll say well why did
it move you know say well because you
pushed it I said well but why else did
it move right and then look at me and
they'll look at me well you wanted to
move no no no no no not that why did it
move and there'll be a silence for a
while and in silence and then when
somebody will say well because there was
like open space in front of it ah ah
like so but why are you so fixated on
the event why can't you see the
constraints that make things possible as
opposed to the events that are making
things act right right so we like we
like even just trying to teach them
something you know this example Asif II
this is just trying to get them to
understand dynamical systems
I have dispersed I have to do this
metaphysical move at the beginning of
the class of getting them to break away
from regarding actuality as a synonym
for reality and just getting them to
break that in their mind then it takes
them some time to do it but once they do
it I can I can I can see this sort of oh
oh and then you see
all these and then they realize all the
possibilities for addressing a lot of
you know sort of really tricky thorny
problems I now have a space in which you
can address them that you couldn't
address them before but it I'm only
pointing out for this because it's just
so how pervasive this way of thinking is
and that's what I like when I read
religion religion and nothing that's for
the first time it just looked like it
really blew my mind because I thought
heidegger's idea about that Ichi just
inverts but I didn't get I needed
something like nishitani to say but
what's different from the like just the
inversion what what's what's the trans
framing for you is one of my terms of
this looked like initiative gave me a
sort of a really
so my first deep understanding of what
that might look like yeah yeah in that
that sense of you know what that that
exercise that you just said so much
demonstrates I think is is the is the
thing that Heidegger is getting at which
is about this whole techno in-frame
movement where it's it's almost like
it's like it this time it figure eise's
everything right so like the moment the
moment the ground right or a background
it it just keeps figure a guy like it's
only valid if it's positionable right
locatable and it's and that's the thing
that's just really I think I keep
finding myself impressed with that that
that sense of know that there's an
intelligibility right there is an
understanding that that I'm inside of
right that organizes everything mmm
which that I don't um
it's not even personal it's something
I'm it's constituting and how things
make sense right
until that motion word that just just
that there's that issue where it's like
well why do you always just figure the
events and you just have to be up to
date sit sit with them to be able to see
that there's a there's a ground that
allows for this that withdrawals that
you can't figure right that that is very
much
well can we can we pick up on that
because that goes towards uh what was it
my first question like that
understanding you're talking about guy
this is what this one I want to sort of
slow down on and try and zoom in on
because that's what I'm trying to get
out about you know something that's
trans categorical that somehow
encompasses it's not it's not orthogonal
to but it's not reducible to any one of
these categories so I'm reducible to the
cognitive or the existential or or the
ontological and I suggested to you that
maybe sacredness is like that and and I
think you're try it sounds to me lets me
speak very clearly carefully it sounds
to me like you're trying to point to a
kind of understanding a kind of
comportment to that kind of trans
categorical sacredness and i think that
we could touch on unpack that together i
think that would be very helpful because
i think that goes towards this issue
about you know what the meaning crisis
is and how it I agreed if we shouldn't
identify the meaning crisis with
nihilism
I think nihilism is a perennial aspect
there's a certain sense in which it is
now you know maybe to use your term guys
worked before grounded or more figured
for people and I would but I still don't
even want to equate that exactly with
the meaning crisis I would say something
like nihilism is an aspect of the
meaning crisis because when I when I'm
pointing to the meaning crisis I'm
trying to point to not just a kind of
what's the word like an event or rights
I'm trying to point to also well I'm
trying to point to all three of these
categories I'm trying to point to the
psychological aspects I'm trying to
point to also the suffering the loss of
agency the distress alright I'm not just
pointing to a particular realization of
that's the right word about our
relationship to being I'm trying to
point out that this this erodes into
certain fundamental aspects of how we
try to do how we how we try to
fundamentally make sense and adopt
agency in the world so it's I think it's
for me it's a it's a larger category
than just what is encompassed by
nihilism in both the popular sense and
and also I think the more profound sense
that we're talking about when we're
talking about sort of the the kyoto
school so so the meaning crisis then is
something distinctly modern something of
this epoch i think so although i would
want to say that there was something
deeply analogous to it in the
Hellenistic period that you have you had
something like that
in which there was you know pervasive
sense this connection of a loss of touch
with realness and there was and this is
where the whole metaphor of the
philosopher as the physician of the
psyche comes into prominence right and
it's actually it's actually the
progenitor of most of our cognitive
therapies today comes out of that
particular meaning crisis and what what
was interesting was the culture was able
to sort of reconfigure philosophy and
what it meant and and then that had
impacts on religion that sort of seemed
to have alleviated a lot of the
suffering and the distress
whereas we seem to be in a place that's
worse off if I can put it that way
because of our disconnection from our
wisdom traditions we don't seem to have
access to the resources we need in order
to bring about the transformations that
are analogous to what happened in the
Hellenistic period so in one sense yes
but yeah I'm gonna say that that's how
I'd answer that question
yeah did this just maybe a brought a
point but this maybe makes it more
accessible what what about it is that
Heidegger means when he speaks of deep
science Ferguson hide the Oblivion of
forgetting of being yes being cut off
from what you would say these resources
of wisdom yes without being totally
divided from and so we try to make sense
by accelerating right over seeing
yourself as workers or giving ourselves
meaning but the trouble kicking God says
if you just give meaning to ourselves or
to something we can throw away that
meaning the next day yes something
deeper it can't just be posited by us
which is the postmodern subjective
that tries to get that get that done but
that totally doesn't work there's
paranoia that maybe kicks into with with
late modern subjectivity now and and
yeah and this sense of being and count
off I think is what perhaps even what
depression indicates worse all right
some well I was gonna say I was gonna
say I mean here's the clear instance of
where you know the existential mode the
wait okay so there's an ontological
thing there's our relationship to being
and then we get our existential mode but
obviously picked up on by like regard
but then you see it connecting to
psychological factors because I mean the
the cognitive science on meaning says
that one of the biggest fun so we tend
to emphasize our culture like to say
that in fact we use this as a synonym
and it also shows again this collapse
into actuality that we've been talking
about right that muck that top my my
might my life is meaningful if I have a
purpose and it's this right it's the
purpose all right now having a sense of
purpose in fact does psychologically
contribute to meaning life but not as
much as a sense of mattering which is a
sense of being connected to something
that is larger than yourself that has a
value independent of your egocentric
desires alright and so it so basically
what it does to put it into a phrase and
this then takes it back into kirkegaard
you'll you'll see why in a sec it
challenged you to it challenges you to
aspire to transformation right because
the only way of appropriately relating
the only way of connecting to something
that you accept is larger than yourself
is through some kind of transformation
some kind of self transcendence right
and so that mattering to people is
actually psychologically crucial but it
takes you into this existential project
of aspirate of the aspiration of self
transcendence and then that puts you
back into the ontological problem of
what the heck does self transcendence
mean in our oncology so that's what I
mean about how I see all three connected
maybe that's a good sort of case study
of exactly what I'm trying to talk about
here
it's yes well I just don't yeah I just I
love what you're what you're put I love
what you're possessed by John I'm sorry
did I just I didn't mean to do I get
overwhelming I just like it
I I'm actually feeling like I'm just a
voice for the the pregnancy of these
connections sneaking themselves right
that like the way that the cognitive and
the existential and the ontological are
all they're not identical I'm not
claiming that I'm not getting a
reduction here but you see how they're
interdependent and therefore the problem
if that's the right word of what would
the issue that we're trying to address
is not one that can simply be addressed
by therapy or even by philosophy in the
academic sense yeah no no no it must be
back in the policy it must be back in in
we're we're philosophy always was
strongest yes yes back in the call it
public sphere whatever but it meets and
it needs to be right when you speak off
but this sense that I matter but I met
her because there's something else that
matters more than than just I yeah a
true sense of awe a sense of dangerous
divinities yes I like that you know God
isn't the reason with the capital R and
we all bow down to our own magnificent
powers but there's something what Heidi
could keeps talking about the uncanny
right yes
yeah I'm Kennie over the world and this
is not a moral statement this is to say
there is something uncanny even just
about existence the sheer fact isset e
of existence is uncanny
but that uncanny ness is an imitation
that on cane is an invitation to think
after what's actually going on and
that's what's very important to me is is
memory is shared if you like in English
I think yes you could say something like
a shared sense of memory that's larger
than just my memory I'm gonna gonna be
leaping around a bit now so apologies
for that but when you think of how
transhumanism for example tries to sell
us in motel
which would mean that all our memories
get shared in the cloud that that's a
copy of yourself that's probably not how
I would think how memory works I think
that memory is much larger its share
there's a extend itself that you
were thrown into and you share in that a
sense of memory that we are being cut
off from because we are basically
encapsulates it isolated pinned down
just on us just me and it's just my
subjectivity that matters I I'm the
ground of my world transformation is
just about optimizing my cells in order
to get better in order to to achieve
this and that but it's never or not
often at least getting back to a certain
sense of understanding again what what
are the fundamental questions off for
example existence and if we do so and
that that would have to accept however
finitude and death and and also certain
powerlessness not an entire
powerlessness but to a certain degree of
powerlessness in the face of existence
itself so that's interesting so there's
two things I want to bring up about that
then so a question is a relationship
between Heidegger sense of the uncanny
and Auto sense of the numinous which
Chris and I talked about quite a bit
they're both post content so it's not
completely irrelevant now and and then
the what what that has to do with again
with this this this thing I'm talking
about the sacredness because presumably
the sacred wood would do exactly what I
said it would give you the psychological
muttering that puts you into the correct
existential mode of aspiration right
that then also gave you a sense of an
affordance of self transcendence that
wasn't just subjective projection that
was in some set had some kind of
connectedness to reality to it and so
that's again helps me to sharpen that a
little bit and so what role does the
like is the uncanny like the numinous or
are they just different ways of the same
thing and then what did and again what
that has to do with collective memory
because one thing I see religions doing
and this has come out in my discussions
with Paul van der clay is they represent
a distributed cognitive memory of
encounters with the sacred right and and
that it's not it doesn't belong to any
one person for precisely that was the
holy idea of ecclesia the body of Christ
right it's it's a car it's a distributed
a thing across time and John cars really
talks about this a lot in his book the
religious case against belief where he
said we've lost that sense of you know
what you actually have you have like
this this I don't know what to call it
it's this sort of structure that keeps
forming around mystery and it sort of
carries it forward and that's how it's
remembered and then we're losing that as
we're trying to solidify and still it in
two sets of beliefs but the point I'm
trying to make is that the churches that
I'm using the church as a categorical
thing you don't mean like the Roman
Catholic Church right it seems to me
that one of the places in which you get
a clear instance of where cultures have
tried to maintain that distributed
collective memory of the encounter with
the uncanny or what I might call the
sacred Rite and had to try and
continually bridge between the cognitive
the existential and the ontological has
precisely been in religions religions in
fact seem to be where you get that kind
of distribute not only distributed
synchronically across people but
diachronic ly across time this is the
whole religious idea of tradition right
tradition seems to be that kind of thing
you're talking about or or am I making a
mistake so I'm hoping in it
no yeah tradition yes it's and and the
trouble is hiding as one and one of the
essays that's not very well known behind
it is on traditional language and
technical language and it happens I
hiding it greatly in language and then
we speak more and more and in terms that
are very technical and not no longer
connect
to the sense of poesis employees and of
course is connected to the sacred
because the sacred means is I would
think means something that you you
simply to let something occur to let
something be let something shine in of
itself and not want it to be in sheer
available actuality for example um and
about also there's a friend of mine
Francesco cottony or just published a
book on Ottawa Nietzsche in Italian
which is presented early they the
presence of the gods right right and for
also there there there is this sheer
presence of the divine in in beings and
I'm not sure so with with Heidegger I
think it's a bit different because for
him the gods remain unnamed and they
remain withdrawn a bit to a certain
degree and I think he's trying to do at
least on my reading I'm not sure if
that's correct but he's trying to in the
four fold is to remind us think about
when he writes this fifties and sixties
he gives public talks to engineers etc
he tells at a time when there was a
great believe that technology could save
us liberate us once and for all we could
have Ito Pia and Adorno at the time and
an sloth talked about how utopia would
come about when we finally give up on
death right so once we become him also
that's when we have utopia or when death
becomes an option for those who want to
die for whatever reason but in that time
I think he reminds the human being of a
simple truth of this capacity of being
mortal and that capacity is only however
possible to even think off when there
are immortals for Heidegger you can
never think one without the other right
there's this this so in hi I'm Kenny and
tremana I'm means moon Heimlich unholy
so the world is unholy but it can also
be homely and yeah that's what I wanted
to get to you know okay because one of
the things you know that Chris and I
thought about is that the sacred seems
to be doing both of these it's
seems to both be a way of homing us
against horror
this is geertz's notion right of the
sacred well at the same time also at
times as you say I'm homing us putting
us outside of that that sense and it
immediates between Ok Go Ahead
this is like this is super because one
of the things I've been thinking about
is horror horror is so important because
the way we think of Horus and we just
you know everyday terms horror is a
movie yeah yeah horror is something in a
film that's horrible for two hours and
then I go home and maybe have a bad
dream but no hora hora and the weird
thing is what happens again thanks to
you mono economy not thanks him
how does he define boredom he calls
boredom the horror bark we the horror of
emptiness which is perhaps a ride in the
horse cart is is rather dull right this
is incredibly bourgeois a definition of
horror but that sort of a cuy but he's
almost like because the Newman what's
what's the nur woman on the the unnamed
that's what it means when can't this -
he's pushing even the essence of things
all the way to an an unnamed outside -
in realm of uncanny maybe to a realm off
of sheer horror - you know HP Lovecraft
you could think of him for example here
but but when you think of this in terms
of Heidegger again in terms of the
history of metaphysics metaphysics
forgets consumers metaphysics forget
self withdrawal maybe metaphysics also
forgets horror maybe this history
forgets this sheer horror that also is
at the heart of existence not only but
also well that gives need to two
connecting points is the way to go back
to circle back to mortality the way
Eastern or easy attic religions I'm
thinking you know especially you know
Indian and Chinese especially Buddhist
but there's the horror of immortality
yes right which which
so you know when I talk to people in the
West about this and I say I try to get
them to understand this idea about the
about how important your mortality is
well no but you know we all they'll say
they'll say as if it's axiomatic but we
all just want to live forever night well
I say well actually you don't and that's
not true about the cultures right other
cultures actually experience the
prospect of immortality as deeply deeply
horrific and and you know you
reincarnation for example is the thing
you're trying to break free from in many
versions of Hinduism and of coke and the
same thing with sort of the desire for
perpetual existence is what binds you
into suffering within Buddhism in
profound ways and so I think I think
what I'm trying to what are the
connection I'm trying to bring it back
to is I think the absence of horror in
our metaphysics is actually a telling
thing I think it again points to the
fact that we are ultimately seeking a
kind of security for our intelligibility
rather than always trying to nourish our
intelligibility through all and I think
those are fundamentally different
projects for us and that's the the the
security I think I and this is where I
think what the responds to is either
grossly the withdrawal of being through
the withdrawal of sense right and and
one of the things I liked in that
interview with your teacher he where he
was talking about the our response right
what is to it to the withdrawal of sense
is ISM is it is to take this hyper
morality position right oh great I'm
sorry it where we go we we experience
the loss of sense but we don't we don't
recognize we we we we compensate for it
by just being really upset about things
right and being offended about things
and what you're saying is you can notice
that like rationality doesn't have it
doesn't even consider rationality no no
in that that that responds to the to the
withdrawal of of the sense of beingness
of the of the fullness of things we
we've excluded from our notion of
rationality edie any sense of this whole
side of the spectrum if I could put it
that way
rationality has has been truncated to
confirmation coherence the idea that
insight and transformation and a
capacity for wonder in Plato's sense not
Aristotle sense because I think for
Aristotle it's for my curiosity for
Plato it's clearly ah that all of these
things are actually crucial to
forgetting for example overcoming all of
this self-deception that our ego
centrism and our narcissism makes us
pray to and they should therefore be
central central to our ideas of
rationality not peripheral things that
are somehow romantically pursued when
our rationality is done what it needs to
do for the day I think that is a very
crucial point what you just did god to
try and that way in which we're talking
again this is again we're talking about
something ontological and then we shift
into the existential and then it
reverberates back into the cognitive now
because now we're bringing up the whole
notion of what what does rationality
because if this is about you know sense
making rationality should be in this
discussion but obviously in a
reformulated way so that it comports
with what we're talking about well and I
think one of the things that I'm if I
feel into it like if I I think one of
the things I like about um about real
what I've gotten out of reading
Heidegger more than his ideas or his
views and it's been to read them is to
walk on the path of looking to that
which reveals it's uncanny nasai wanted
to ask you about that yeah it's a almost
like it's been a practice for me well
wholly but I
found that to be the case and I think I
did work I had to go would actually like
me saying this so there's maybe a bit of
a a performative pun here I found that
to be the case with all of the really
great philosophers like I find you don't
read Spinoza
yeah you you base you you you you I
don't know what you immerse yourself in
Spinoza until like you you got you
I'm gonna use this word because I think
it's appropriate you have to read you
have to reads for knows you have to
recite to knows it to yourself
religiously you have to you have to go
through like if you don't get scans get
to atiba when you're reading you if it
doesn't occur to you then I use all and
all you've got is the arguments of
Spinoza
I think you've missed the ethics I think
you didn't miss the ethics yeah same
thing with Plato right for like Plato is
sacred to me because like I can keep
following Plato I can I can go to Plato
I get insight I get transfer I get the
challenge to transformation I go out in
the world the world discloses itself to
me in a way that it couldn't before that
transforms me I go back to Plato and
then I see something again in Plato that
I didn't see and I can and so Plato
engenders and agog a Spinoza engenders
can see Intuit eva i think the great
philosophers engender again this a state
that's between and beyond the cognitive
the existential and the ontological they
put you into this place i'm struggling
for words here that isn't captured by
those categories and that's the thing of
any great philosopher is to get to that
place with them right and that's in mmm
I think I'm right I think I to do would
like that sorry to interrupt you but the
great philosophers yeah it's I think
what you're describing is what you could
call the apparition of thinking right
yes there's nothing and this is this is
what I thought philosophy would be yes
yes
dee Mia and it was a bit like that with
evil
did you now don't need to leap but it's
because very small University and I came
here and it was a bit different but it's
it's
yeah I think that's ultimately how
philosophy should be taught but I don't
care is it this isn't but that isn't
that's not ultimately that important
it's not that important what by the way
you might disagree with Plato and some
things of others but what is it then why
is it these texts and the way we do and
what is it that they do with us and why
do we why is it that we can come back to
them again and again and again it must
actually I've read the cave at aghori I
don't know how many time exactly exactly
still I'm reading it I could read every
week and I would still all right I
forgot oh really this is every single
time yeah yes yeah God back to you
because I cut you off I'm sorry about
that I just was wondering if we look at
I think I really want to like I think
this is exciting because it's drawing I
think it may be bringing something
together if we look at what is it that
happens in that relationship of reading
of philosopher right like what are we
exercising and I'm wondering if it
touches it on the ontological like the
cognitive and the existential these
throwing so that's that's what I'm
saying and and then and then for me and
of course you you probably first saw
that I was going to do this guy this
then translates also into deal logos as
something that's happening between
people and also has that and so there's
something right there and it's no
coincidence that you know Plato writes
dialogues right that it's not a
coincidence that is not a coincidence
there's something about what we're doing
here and how you should read a
philosopher they need each other this is
what I mean about when you know this
what this is a deep meaning of what I'm
trying to I'm trying to work on with you
guy about trying to bring philosophy a--
not academic philosophy but philosophy
a-- into like into circling and to get
the two of them you know working
together you know the what's happening
in the circling feeds into reading the
philosophers and reading the
philosophers feeds back into that that's
that's that's the project i'm
all right now exam with you right does
all the text they send you yeah I did
Chester was bought the last one you gave
me I'm sorry
it was written it was very good by the
way it was very good so I think that I
think the thing about well it's actually
like bringing in the conversation that
he had with Andrew what I was reading
with you about the second conversation
in conversation I really really got at a
deeper level this is sense of what was
it um how rationality is rationing for
where to bring your attention that
reveals wisdom right
yeah the rationing and the ratty oh yeah
gimme that it's it has as much to do
with logistics as it does to do with
logic yeah and and and and and the
proportioning isn't like just a copy it
isn't just an intellectual proportioning
it's like it's like in the four fold the
correct proportioning of human beings to
the gods and to the earth
that's Rati oh right that's right here
right because it's closer to it's much
closer like I say to logos and all that
was you know the best our best word from
another culture is Dharma Dharma is a
word like Buddhism that has all of that
kind of sense do it right
yes and that just I just really just got
that sense of oh that there's a way that
there's a way of listening right that
there's a way it's it seems like
listening seems to be the right metaphor
here right
I like arcanine better I like your
harkening better because for me
harkening carries with it the sense of
also a receptivity and and and a making
one's oneself sensitive long more
vulnerable and opening and listening
doesn't connote that for me the way
harkening de because hearken ii like
it's a bit and your hearken is a call to
you right
ah listen to the call and that there's
something about it where is where I
think this is starts to Britt this is
starts to be break free of the
metaphysics right mmm because it's it to
here is is to be unclear about what
you're hearing but yet to be a tune to
what you can't quite make out yet right
that would whisper ring to you and to to
be or because this is one of things I
noticed encircling and leading circling
of just I noticed this last weekend is
just sitting with people and and
harkening so what is the what are they
what what's really present what's really
present and just tuning into that is I
can I kept feeling this sense of in this
growing sense of tuning in to the
movement of showing or something like
the that's in is there's an orientation
that just keeps drawing it it has an
auto poetic quality to it yes yes object
is not looking for an object or an
answer it's something else just at the
edge of intelligibility or it reminds me
I I was circling last night it remind I
so I said I want to follow the circle
where it goes but I was invoking
Socrates is a point of follow the
argument wherever it goes that that's
that's the that kind of sense yeah I
wanna I want to hear what you Hannes us
to say but I want to ask you one
question guy first so and this goes to
the point we were just on I don't want
to leave you yet because I sort of
brought this up like sort of post
circling I would say saying you know
we're hearkening to each other and we're
even harkening you know to the third
factor that's opening between us but but
it seems to me there's another like I
said you know I have an allegiance to to
you the people are circling with an
allegiance to or the process but I also
want to be able to I think this is part
of being an authentically participating
it I want to be able to engage my
allegiance to the topics that might
emerge yes so for example
one one person sort of brought up sort
of brought the circling practice itself
into question yeah right and what
happened is people just did the circling
and they sort of tune into each other
and I was kind of like you know no I
didn't that no no no no that's a no
that's a lost opportunity you know we we
we should keep the circle going but
there you know that person wants to
wonder about circling rather than just
wonder within circling and those aren't
the same thing and they should be put
into a dialogue with each other and you
know what is it what does that mean like
to subtract and like and you know and
then what happened is we didn't started
this discourse around circling which you
know that's what I mean about against
trying to get these things to talk to
each other we should both let Johannes
say something though he's been very
patient and kind with us I think um just
briefly on
harkening I had not thought of this I'd
always just you know use the word to
listen to I will from now on say harken
it's also much closer to Hulk and Hulk
right which is listen but harken in a
proper that you have to now really hear
what I'm saying yes and what we now
think of as the third where we've
classified as the first fragment of
Heraclitus livid actually was his first
fragment we don't know he speaks of a
cooing so he speaks of the logos and
that we yes yes we are in a hearing
stance to the bill got yeah yeah but
we're not listening or now I would say
harkening yeah so this is one of the
oldest wisdoms that we have or right
testimonials of logos is that logos can
be hearkened there's something as always
a hearing that's always something
addressing us calling us yeah but what
we must do is respond we must respond
and that's ultimately beautifully in
English to say this because you can say
that's responsibility yes there is this
deep sense of responsibility you
mustn't be cut off from and it has to do
altima t i think with with with the
ecstatic temporalities of history itself
that's something that I that I see in
encircling happening because it works
with what has been comes back towards
you the old time right this is all the
time and I think this is how this really
works itself and what what we've done is
we've we've made linear history and
assume that we just move on into an
empty feel that we can that will
rearrange and make make it just around
where we please and we've completely
forgotten that that which has been is
still coming back and maybe not just you
know to haunt us but also to give us
again a sense of direction it's all the
hands it's like we've been Heidegger
says if ever Minden to get over instead
of overcome instead of over we were
common so so tame technics
and framing must be finding that means
you don't go over it you go right in and
then you turn it from within because
it's not about getting rid of it it's
about understanding where it comes from
hiding who keep saying it does have an
origin we must find that origin because
if not them we're cut off and that means
we live in Amity in a meaningless world
it's quite vacuum huh that's that just
that notion of origin right what I the
picture I get from how I hear that is
it's like different and source right
source has kind of like a from to right
sense to it origin has more of this it's
somehow present right now right it's
like somehow present underneath the
origin of something I can add the sense
of where I can reveal the set the origin
yeah of this sentence or the origin of
this moment there's a
there is this kind of quality to it we
carry that in the adjective original
yeah we mean it's a current it's a
property that something can currently
have that points back to his origin
right so there's a there is that sense
in the adjective to say that something's
original is actually to talk about how
it is now even though you're presumably
referring to something in its past yeah
I agree with you
original does carry that same origin
does carry that sense with it mm-hmm
yeah origin is a is like this right in
terms of the hand
it's the wellspring of meaning yeah it's
it's it's not the source right we said
that could give rise to being a resource
etc which then could be sound like we're
exploiting it but no origin and this is
what hiding keeps coming back to when he
says the origin is not something two and
a half thousand years ago I'm not saying
go back to the Golden Age of the Greeks
know there is something of origin
waiting in these texts in these
testimonials of logos of knowledge of
ratio and of being itself of course that
there's still something to be found in
them right and and the other way of
dealing with philosophy so we've made
this distinction John you made a
situation between if you go Sofia of
course the love of wisdom and academic
philosophy now it was Afiya means okay
there's a sense of origin there's
something there there's something
there's something there when I read
these texts I come to these texts not
not to be right or to find the place who
was wrong but to be transformed by this
because there must be a reason why Plato
is Plato right and what I see in
academic philosophy now is something
else which is in my mind a bit cut off
from origin because what we now see is
Spinoza a realist so is he more of an
idealist if he is an idealist is he a
Dogma etcetera whatever he is some kind
of isn't that that's no longer this
sense of an original access to this
because ultimately this isn't don't
matter what matters is something else
and that's this sense of getting back in
touch with what there is
with meaning let's just say